BASIC SYNTAX

PHP tags
	- When PHP parses a file, it looks for opening and closing tags, which are <?php and ?> which tell PHP to start and stop interpreting the code between them.
	- If pure PHP code it is preferable to used the PHP closing tag, this will prevents accidental whitespace or new lines being added after the PHP closing tag. Causing different effects because PHP will start output buffering when there is no intention from the programmer to send and output at that point in the script.

<?php
 echo "Hello World";

//... more code

 echo "last Statement";

// the script ends here with no PHP closing tag

========================================================================
Escaping from HTML

<p>This is going to be ignored by PHP and displayed by the browser. </p>

<?php echo 'While this is going to be parsed.';?>

<p> This will also be ignored by PHP and displayed by the browser. </p>

	- when the PHP interpreter hits the ?> closing tags, it simply starts outputting whatever it finds until it hits another opening tag unless in the middle of a conditional statement in which case the interpreter will determine the outcome of the conditional before making a decision of what to skip over.

	Advanced escaping using conditions
		<?php if ($expression == true): ?>
  			This will show if the expression is true.
		<?php else: ?>
  			Otherwise this will show.
		<?php endif; ?>
	
	- PHP will skip the blocks where the condition is not met. PHP skips them according to the condition since the PHP interpreter will jump over blocks contained within a condition that is not met.

	- In PHP 5, there are up to five different pairs of opening and closing tags available in PHP, depending on how PHP is configured. Two of these, <?php ?> and <script language="php"> </script>, are always available. There is also the short echo tag <?= ?>, which is always available in PHP 5.4.0 and later.

*Also note that if you are embedding PHP within XML or XHTML you will need to use the <?php ?> tags to remain compliant with standards.

	-PHP 7 removes support for ASP tags and <script language="php"> tags. As such, we recommend only using <?php ?> and <?= ?> when writing PHP code to maximise compatibility.

1.  <?php echo 'if you want to serve PHP code in XHTML or XML documents,
                use these tags'; ?>

2.  You can use the short echo tag to <?= 'print this string' ?>.
    It's always enabled in PHP 5.4.0 and later, and is equivalent to
    <?php echo 'print this string' ?>.

3.  <? echo 'this code is within short tags, but will only work '.
            'if short_open_tag is enabled'; ?>

4.  <script language="php">
        echo 'some editors (like FrontPage) don\'t
              like processing instructions within these tags';
    </script>
    This syntax is removed in PHP 7.0.0.

5.  <% echo 'You may optionally use ASP-style tags'; %>
    Code within these tags <%= $variable; %> is a shortcut for this code <% echo $variable; %>
    Both of these syntaxes are removed in PHP 7.0.0.

	- ASP style tags (example five) are only available when they are enabled via the asp_tags php.ini configuration file directive, and have been removed in PHP 7.0.0.

*Using short tags should be avoided when developing applications or libraries that are meant for redistribution, or deployment on PHP servers which are not under your control, because short tags may not be supported on the target server. For portable, redistributable code, be sure not to use short tags.

========================================================================
Instruction Separation

	- You do not need to used a semicolon to terminating the last line of a PHP block. The closing tag for the block will include the immediately trailing newline if one is present.

<?php
    echo 'This is a test';
?>

<?php echo 'This is a test' ?>

<?php echo 'We omitted the last closing tag';

*Using a closing tag is optional but and some cases this is helpful when usung include or require, so unwanted whitespace will not occur at the end of files, and you will still be able to add headers to the response later.

========================================================================
Comments

<?php
    echo 'This is a test'; // This is a one-line c++ style comment
    /* This is a multi line comment
       yet another line of comment */
    echo 'This is yet another test';
    echo 'One Final Test'; # This is a one-line shell-style comment
?>

	-The “one-l ine” comment style remarks only PHP codes either the current block or the end of the line, whichever comes first, meaning HTML code with // … ?> or # … ?> before them will be printed; having ?> on the other hand breaks out PHP mode returning it to HTML mode while // or # doesn’t affect it. The asp_tags configuration directive acts the same with // %> and # %> when being enabled but the </script> tag cannot break out PHP mode in a one-line comment.

====================================================================================================================================================

TYPES

Introduction

PHP supports ten primitive types. 

Four Scalar types:

	- boolean
		- Considered as the simplest type in which it only gives a correct value whether it’s TRUE or FALSE.

	SYNTAX
	<?php
	$foo = True; // assign the value TRUE to $foo
	?>
	
	Converting to Boolean 
		- In converting a value to boolean, (bool) or (boolean) casts is being used but sometimes the cast is dispensable because the value will be converted right away by an operator or control structure requiring a boolean argument.

		- When converting to boolean, the following values are considered FALSE:

			- the boolean FALSE itself
			- the integer 0 (zero)
			- the float 0.0 (zero)
			- the empty string, and the string "0"
			- an array with zero elements
			- the special type NULL (including unset variables)
			- SimpleXML objects created from empty tags
			- Every other value is considered TRUE (including any resource and NAN).

	*-1 is considered TRUE, like any other non-zero (whether negative or positive) number!

-----------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------

	- integer

Syntax
	- Different types of integers are as follows:

Decimal – base 10
Hexadecimal – base 16, begin the number with 0x in using this notation
Octal – base 8, begin the number with 0 in using this notation
Binary – base 2, begin the number with 0b in using this notation

Can also be preceded by a sign (- or +).

	Integer literals

	<?php
	$a = 1234; // decimal number
	$a = -123; // a negative number
	$a = 0123; // octal number (equivalent to 83 decimal)
	$a = 0x1A; // hexadecimal number (equivalent to 26 decimal)
	$a = 0b11111111; // binary number (equivalent to 255 decimal)
	?>

Formally, the structure for integer literals is:

decimal     : [1-9][0-9]*
            | 0

hexadecimal : 0[xX][0-9a-fA-F]+

octal       : 0[0-7]+

binary      : 0[bB][01]+

integer     : [+-]?decimal
            | [+-]?hexadecimal
            | [+-]?octal
            | [+-]?binary

Integer Overflow

	- Number that exceeds the integer type experienced by the PHP will be interpreted as a float likewise with the operation having a number beyond the bounds of the integer type will return a float.

Integer overflow on a 32-bit system

	<?php
	$large_number = 2147483647;
	var_dump($large_number);                     // int(2147483647)

	$large_number = 2147483648;
	var_dump($large_number);                     // float(2147483648)

	$million = 1000000;
	$large_number =  50000 * $million;
	var_dump($large_number);                     // float(50000000000)
	?>	

Integer overflow on a 64-bit system

	<?php
	$large_number = 9223372036854775807;
	var_dump($large_number);                     // int(9223372036854775807)

	$large_number = 9223372036854775808;
	var_dump($large_number);                     // float(9.2233720368548E+18)

	$million = 1000000;
	$large_number =  50000000000000 * $million;
	var_dump($large_number);                     // float(5.0E+19)
	?>

		- There is no integer division operator in PHP. 1/2 yields the float 0.5. The value can be casted to an integer to round it towards zero, or the round() function provides finer control over rounding.

Converting to Integer

	From booleans 
		FALSE will yield 0 (zero), and TRUE will yield 1 (one).

	From floating point numbers 
		When converting from float to integer, the number will be rounded towards zero.

	- CCasts such as (int) or (integer) is used when converting a value to integer but in some parts of it, cast is not necessary because the value will automatically be converted when an operator requires an integer argument. Intval() function can converts a value to integer also.
If a resource is converted to an integer, then the result will be the unique resource number assigned to the resource by PHP at runtime.

*Never cast an unknown fraction to integer, as this can sometimes lead to unexpected results.

<?php
echo (int) ( (0.1+0.7) * 10 ); // echoes 7!
?>

--------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------

- float (floating-point number, aka double)
		- Floating point numbers which are also known as "floats", "doubles", or "real numbers" can be classified using any of the following syntaxes:
			<?php
			$a = 1.234; 
			$b = 1.2e3; 
			$c = 7E-10;
				?>
	Formally:

		LNUM          [0-9]+
		DNUM          ([0-9]*[\.]{LNUM}) | ({LNUM}[\.][0-9]*)
		EXPONENT_DNUM [+-]?(({LNUM} | {DNUM}) [eE][+-]? {LNUM})

	- The size of a float is platform-dependent, although a maximum of ~1.8e308 with a precision of roughly 14 decimal digits is a common value (the 64 bit IEEE format).

	Converting to float
		- Other types of values conversion is being done by converting first the value to integer then to float. As of PHP 5, a notice is thrown if an object is converted to float.

	Comparing Float
		- Equality is difficult to be done sometimes with testing floating point values because of how it is being illustrated internally but knowing the differentiation of floating point values that works around these limitations has a way.

		- In testing the floating point values for equality, upper bound on the relative error due to rounding known as the machine epsilon or unit roundoff used, making it as the smallest acceptable difference in calculations.

		$a and $b are equal to 5 digits of precision.

			<?php
			$a = 1.23456789;
			$b = 1.23456780;
			$epsilon = 0.00001;

			if(abs($a-$b) < $epsilon) {
			    echo "true";
			}
			?>

	Nan
	- Some numeric operations can result in a value represented by the constant NAN. This result represents an undefined value in floating-point calculations. Any loose or strict comparisons of this value against any other value, including itself, but except TRUE, will have a result of FALSE.

	- NAN represents any number of different values and should not be compared to other values, including itself instead it should be checked for using is_nan().

----------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------
	- string(not done)
		-A string is a series of character that are same as a byte. PHP only supports a 256-character set and does not offer native Unicode support.

	SYNTAX
		- single quoted
			- Simplest way in knowing a string is to enclose it in a single quotes(the character ‘)

			- In specifying a literal single quote, escape it with a backslash (\) and to specify a literal backslash, double it (\\).All other instances of backslash will be treated as a literal backslash. Meaning, the other escape sequences you might be used to, such as \r or \n, will be output literally as specified rather than having any special meaning.

	<?php
	echo 'this is a simple string';

	echo 'You can also have embedded newlines in 
	strings this way as it is
	okay to do';

	// Outputs: Arnold once said: "I'll be back"
	echo 'Arnold once said: "I\'ll be back"';

	// Outputs: You deleted C:\*.*?
	echo 'You deleted C:\\*.*?';

	// Outputs: You deleted C:\*.*?
	echo 'You deleted C:\*.*?';

	// Outputs: This will not expand: \n a newline
	echo 'This will not expand: \n a newline';

	// Outputs: Variables do not $expand $either
	echo 'Variables do not $expand $either';
	?>

		- double quoted
			- PHP will interpret the following escape sequences for special characters if the string is enclosed in double-quotes (‘’)

			Escaped characters

	Sequence	Meaning
	\n		linefeed (LF or 0x0A (10) in ASCII)
	\r		carriage return (CR or 0x0D (13) in ASCII)
	\t		horizontal tab (HT or 0x09 (9) in ASCII)
	\v		vertical tab (VT or 0x0B (11) in ASCII) (since PHP 5.2.5)
	\e		escape (ESC or 0x1B (27) in ASCII) (since PHP 5.4.4)
	\f		form feed (FF or 0x0C (12) in ASCII) (since PHP 5.2.5)
	\\		backslash
	\$		dollar sign
	\"		double-quote
	\[0-7]{1,3}	the sequence of characters matching the regular 	expression is a character in octal notation, which silently overflows to fit in a byte (e.g. "\400" === "\000")
	\x[0-9A-Fa-f]{1,2}	the sequence of characters matching the regular expression is a character in hexadecimal notation
	\u{[0-9A-Fa-f]+}	the sequence of characters matching the regular expression is a Unicode codepoint, which will be output to the string as that codepoint's UTF-8 representation (added in PHP 7.0.0)

Avoiding any other character in single quoted strings will result in the backslash being printed too. The backslash in \{$var} had not been printed before in PHP 5.1.1.

		- heredoc syntax
			- Another way of delimiting strings is the herodic syntax: <<<. An identifier is given after this operator then a newline. The string itself follows, and then the same identifier again to close the quotation.

			- The closing identifier must begin in the first column of the line. Also, the identifier must follow the same naming rules as any other label in PHP: it must contain only alphanumeric characters and underscores, and must start with a non-digit character or underscore.

Invalid example
	<?php
	class foo {
	    public $bar = <<<EOT
	bar
	    EOT;
	}
	// Identifier must not be indented
	?>

Valid example

	<?php
	class foo {
	    public $bar = <<<EOT
	bar
	EOT;
	}
	?>

	- Herodic text acts like a double-quoted string but having no double quotes. It tells us that herodic is not too necessary to be escapes but the listed escape codes above can still be used. Variables are expanded, but the same care must be taken when expressing complex variables inside a heredoc as with strings.

Herodoc string quoting example

	<?php
	$str = <<<EOD
	Example of string
	spanning multiple lines
	using heredoc syntax.
	EOD;

	/* More complex example, with variables. */
	class foo
	{
 	   var $foo;
 	   var $bar;

	   function __construct()
	   {
	        $this->foo = 'Foo';
	        $this->bar = array('Bar1', 'Bar2', 'Bar3');
 	   }
	}

	foo = new foo();
	$name = 'MyName';

	echo <<<EOT
	My name is "$name". I am printing some $foo->foo.
	Now, I am printing some {$foo->bar[1]}.
	This should print a capital 'A': \x41
	EOT;
	?>

The above example will output:

	My name is "MyName". I am printing some Foo.
	Now, I am printing some Bar2.
	This should print a capital 'A': A

	- Using the Herodic syntax to pass data to function arguments is also possible.

Heredoc in arguments example
	<?php
	var_dump(array(<<<EOD
	foobar!
	EOD
	));
	?>
	- It is possible to initialize static variables and class properties/constants using the Heredoc syntax when reaching PHP 5.3.0.

Using Heredoc to initialize static values

	<?php
	// Static variables
	function foo()
	{
	    static $bar = <<<LABEL
	Nothing in here...
	LABEL;
	}

	// Class properties/constants
	class foo
	{
 	   const BAR = <<<FOOBAR
	Constant example
	FOOBAR;

	    public $baz = <<<FOOBAR
	Property example
	FOOBAR;
	}
	?>

	- Herodic identifier’s opening can be enclosed in PHP 5.3.0 with double quotes by choice.

Using double qoutes in Heredoc

	<?php
	echo <<<"FOOBAR"
	Hello World!
	FOOBAR;
	?>

		- nowdoc syntax 
			- While herodocs are double-quoted strings, nowdocs are single-quoted strings but the parsing is not done inside it. Its construct is good for embedding PHP code or other language without escaping. It shares some features in common with the SGML <![CDATA[ ]]> construct, in that it declares a block of text which is not for parsing.

			- A nowdoc sequence is the same as the herodocs but the identifier is enclosed in single quotes which follows(example: <<<’EOT’. Rules in herodoc can also be used with nowdoc identifiers, especially those regarding the appearance of the closing identifier.

Nowdoc string quoting example

	<?php
	$str = <<<'EOD'
	Example of string
	spanning multiple lines
	using nowdoc syntax.
	EOD;

	/* More complex example, with variables. */
	class foo
	{
 	   public $foo;
	    public $bar;

 	   function __construct()
 	   {
 	       $this->foo = 'Foo';
 	       $this->bar = array('Bar1', 'Bar2', 'Bar3');
 	   }
	}

	$foo = new foo();
	$name = 'MyName';

	echo <<<'EOT'
	My name is "$name". I am printing some $foo->foo.
	Now, I am printing some {$foo->bar[1]}.
	This should not print a capital 'A': \x41
	EOT;
	?>

The above example will output:

	My name is "$name". I am printing some $foo->foo.
	Now, I am printing some {$foo->bar[1]}.
	This should not print a capital 'A': \x41

Static data example

	<?php
	class foo {
	    public $bar = <<<'EOT'
	bar
	EOT;
	}
	?>

Variable parsing
	- When a string is specified in double quotes or with heredoc, variables are parsed within it.

	- Simple and complex are the two categories of syntax. Considering that simple syntax as the simplest and most convenient, it also provides a way to embed variable, an array value, or an object property in a string with a minimum of effort while the complex syntax can be identified base on the curly braces surrounding the expression. To further analyse the difference of the two we sighted some examples to be considered:

	Simple syntax
		- The parser will greedily take as many tokens as possible to form a valid variable name when a dollar sign ($) is encountered. In specifying clearly the end of the name, enclose the variable name in curly braces ({}).

	<?php
	$juice = "apple";

	echo "He drank some $juice juice.".PHP_EOL;
	// Invalid. "s" is a valid character for a variable name, but the variable is $juice.
	echo "He drank some juice made of $juices.";
	// Valid. Explicitly specify the end of the variable name by enclosing it in braces:
	echo "He drank some juice made of ${juice}s.";
	?>

The above example will output:

	He drank some apple juice.
	He drank some juice made of .
	He drank some juice made of apples.

	- Also, an array index or an object property can be parsed. The closing square bracket(]) indicates the end of the index with array indices. Rules in object properties can be applied also in simple variables.

Simple syntax example

	<?php
	$juices = array("apple", "orange", "koolaid1" => "purple");

	echo "He drank some $juices[0] juice.".PHP_EOL;
	echo "He drank some $juices[1] juice.".PHP_EOL;
	echo "He drank some $juices[koolaid1] juice.".PHP_EOL;

	class people {
	   public $john = "John Smith";
 	   public $jane = "Jane Smith";
 	   public $robert = "Robert Paulsen";
    
 	   public $smith = "Smith";
	}

	$people = new people();

	echo "$people->john drank some $juices[0] juice.".PHP_EOL;
	echo "$people->john then said hello to $people->jane.".PHP_EOL;
	echo "$people->john's wife greeted $people->robert.".PHP_EOL;
	echo "$people->robert greeted the two $people->smiths."; // Won't work
	?>

The above example will output:

	He drank some apple juice.
	He drank some orange juice.
	He drank some purple juice.
	John Smith drank some apple juice.
	John Smith then said hello to Jane Smith.
	John Smith's wife greeted Robert Paulsen.
	Robert Paulsen greeted the two .

Negative numeric indices

	<?php
	$string = 'string';
	echo "The character at index -2 is $string[-2].", PHP_EOL;
	$string[-3] = 'o';
	echo "Changing the character at index -3 to o gives $string.", PHP_EOL;
	?>

The above example will output:

	The character at index -2 is n.
	Changing the character at index -3 to o gives strong.

For anything more complex, you should use the complex syntax.

Complex (curly) syntax

	- Any scalar variable, array element or object property with a string representation can be included via this syntax. Simply write the expression the same way as it would appear outside the string, and then wrap it in { and }. Since { can not be escaped, this syntax will only be recognised when the $ immediately follows the {. Use {\$ to get a literal {$. The access to class properties is also possible with the use of variables that are within strings with the use of the syntax.

	<?php
	// Show all errors
	error_reporting(E_ALL);

	$great = 'fantastic';

	// Won't work, outputs: This is { fantastic}
	echo "This is { $great}";

	// Works, outputs: This is fantastic
	echo "This is {$great}";

	// Works
	echo "This square is {$square->width}00 centimeters broad."; 


	// Works, quoted keys only work using the curly brace syntax
	echo "This works: {$arr['key']}";


	// Works
	echo "This works: {$arr[4][3]}";

	// This is wrong for the same reason as $foo[bar] is wrong  outside a string.
	// In other words, it will still work, but only because PHP first looks for a
	// constant named foo; an error of level E_NOTICE (undefined constant) will be
	// thrown.
	echo "This is wrong: {$arr[foo][3]}"; 

	// Works. When using multi-dimensional arrays, always use braces around arrays
	// when inside of strings
	echo "This works: {$arr['foo'][3]}";

	// Works.
	echo "This works: " . $arr['foo'][3];

	echo "This works too: {$obj->values[3]->name}";

	echo "This is the value of the var named $name: {${$name}}";

	echo "This is the value of the var named by the return value of getName(): {${getName()}}";

	echo "This is the value of the var named by the return value of \$object->getName(): {${$object->getName()}}";

	// Won't work, outputs: This is the return value of getName(): {getName()}
	echo "This is the return value of getName(): {getName()}";
	?>

It is also possible to access class properties using variables within strings using this syntax.

	<?php
	class foo {
	    var $bar = 'I am bar.';
	}

	$foo = new foo();
	$bar = 'bar';
	$baz = array('foo', 'bar', 'baz', 'quux');
	echo "{$foo->$bar}\n";
	echo "{$foo->{$baz[1]}}\n";
	?>

The above example will output:

	I am bar.
	I am bar.


	<?php
	// Show all errors.
	error_reporting(E_ALL);

	class beers {
	    const softdrink = 'rootbeer';
 	   public static $ale = 'ipa';
	}

	$rootbeer = 'A & W';
	$ipa = 'Alexander Keith\'s';

	// This works; outputs: I'd like an A & W
	echo "I'd like an {${beers::softdrink}}\n";

	// This works too; outputs: I'd like an Alexander Keith's
	echo "I'd like an {${beers::$ale}}\n";
	?>

String access and modification by character

	- With the use of square array brackets, Characters within strings may be accessed and modified by stating the zero-based offset of the chosen character after the string , as shown in  $str[42]. Think of a string as an array of characters for this purpose. The functions substr() and substr_replace() can be utilized when you want to replace more than 1 character.

	Some string examples
	
	<?php
	// Get the first character of a string
	$str = 'This is a test.';
	$first = $str[0];

	// Get the third character of a string
	$third = $str[2];

	// Get the last character of a string.
	$str = 'This is still a test.';
	$last = $str[strlen($str)-1]; 

	// Modify the last character of a string
	$str = 'Look at the sea';
	$str[strlen($str)-1] = 'e';

	?>

String offsets must be integers or integer-like strings in PHP 5.4. If not, a warning will be thrown. Previously an offset like “foo” was silently cast to 0.

Differences between PHP 5.3 and PHP 5.4

	<?php
	$str = 'abc';

	var_dump($str['1']);
	var_dump(isset($str['1']));

	var_dump($str['1.0']);
	var_dump(isset($str['1.0']));

	var_dump($str['x']);
	var_dump(isset($str['x']));

	var_dump($str['1x']);
	var_dump(isset($str['1x']));
	?>
	Output of the above example in PHP 5.3:

	string(1) "b"
	bool(true)
	string(1) "b"
	bool(true)
	string(1) "a"
	bool(true)
	string(1) "b"
	bool(true)
	Output of the above example in PHP 5.4:

	string(1) "b"
	bool(true)

	Warning: Illegal string offset '1.0' in /tmp/t.php on line 7
	string(1) "b"
	bool(false)

	Warning: Illegal string offset 'x' in /tmp/t.php on line 9
	string(1) "a"
	bool(false)
	string(1) "b"
	bool(false)

* Note:
Accessing variables of other types (not including arrays or objects implementing the appropriate interfaces) using [] or {} silently returns NULL.

Useful functions and operators

	- Strings may be concatenated using the '.' (dot) operator. Note that the '+' (addition) operator will not work for this. There are a number of useful functions for string manipulation.

Converting to string 

	- A value can be converted to a string using the (string) cast or the strval() function. String conversion is automatically done in the scope of an expression where a string is needed. This happens when using the echo or print functions, or when a variable is compared to a string. The sections on Types and Type Juggling will make the following clearer.

	- A boolean TRUE value is converted to the string "1". Boolean FALSE is converted to "" (the empty string). This allows conversion back and forth between boolean and string values.

	- An integer or float is converted to a string representing the number textually (including the exponent part for floats). Floating point numbers can be converted using exponential notation (4.1E+6).

	- Arrays are always converted to the string "Array"; because of this, echo and print can not by themselves show the contents of an array. To view a single element, use a construction such as echo $arr['foo']. 

	- In order to convert objects to string magic method __toString must be used.

	- Resources are always converted to strings with the structure "Resource id #1", where 1 is the resource number assigned to the resource by PHP at runtime. While the exact structure of this string should not be relied on and is subject to change, it will always be unique for a given resource within the lifetime of a script being executed (ie a Web request or CLI process) and won't be reused. To get a resource's type, use the get_resource_type() function.

	- NULL is always converted to an empty string.

	- As stated above, directly converting an array, object, or resource to a string does not provide any useful information about the value beyond its type. 

	- Most PHP values can also be converted to strings for permanent storage. This method is called serialization, and is performed by the serialize() function. If the PHP engine was built with WDDX support, PHP values can also be serialized as well-formed XML text.

String conversion to numbers

	- The outcome value and type is being known when a string is evaluated in a numeric context.

	- The string will be analysed as an integer if the string doesn’t have any of the characters ‘.’, ‘e’, or ‘E’ with the numeric value fits into integer type limits(as defined by PHP_INT_MAX). It will also be evaluated in other cases as float.

	- The value is given by the initial portion of the string. If the string starts with valid numeric data, this will be the value used. Otherwise, the value will be 0 (zero). Valid numeric data is an optional sign, followed by one or more digits (optionally containing a decimal point), followed by an optional exponent. The exponent is an 'e' or 'E' followed by one or more digits.
	
	<?php
	$foo = 1 + "10.5";                // $foo is float (11.5)
	$foo = 1 + "-1.3e3";              // $foo is float (-1299)
	$foo = 1 + "bob-1.3e3";           // $foo is integer (1)
	$foo = 1 + "bob3";                // $foo is integer (1)
	$foo = 1 + "10 Small Pigs";       // $foo is integer (11)
	$foo = 4 + "10.2 Little Piggies"; // $foo is float (14.2)
	$foo = "10.0 pigs " + 1;          // $foo is float (11)
	$foo = "10.0 pigs " + 1.0;        // $foo is float (11)     
	?>

To test any of the examples in this section, cut and paste the examples and insert the following line to see what's going on:

	<?php
	echo "\$foo==$foo; type is " . gettype ($foo) . "<br />\n";
	?>
	- Do not expect to get the code of one character by converting it to integer, as is done in C. Use the ord() and chr() functions to convert between ASCII codes and characters.

Details of the String Type

	- The string in PHP is implemented as an array of bytes and an integer indicating the length of the buffer. It has no information about how those bytes translate to characters, leaving that task to the programmer. There are no limitations on the values the string can be composed of; in particular, bytes with value 0 (“NUL bytes”) are allowed anywhere in the string (however, a few functions, said in this manual not to be “binary safe”, may hand off the strings to libraries that ignore data after a NUL byte.)

	- This nature of the string type explains why there is no separate “byte” type in PHP – strings take this role. Functions that return no textual data – for instance, arbitrary data read from a network socket – will still return strings.

	- Given that PHP does not dictate a specific encoding for strings, one might wonder how string literals are encoded. For instance, is the string "á" equivalent to "\xE1" (ISO-8859-1), "\xC3\xA1" (UTF-8, C form), "\x61\xCC\x81" (UTF-8, D form) or any other possible representation? The answer is that string will be encoded in whatever fashion it is encoded in the script file. Thus, if the script is written in ISO-8859-1, the string will be encoded in ISO-8859-1 and so on. However, this does not apply if Zend Multibyte is enabled; in that case, the script may be written in an arbitrary encoding (which is explicity declared or is detected) and then converted to a certain internal encoding, which is then the encoding that will be used for the string literals. Note that there are some constraints on the encoding of the script (or on the internal encoding, should Zend Multibyte be enabled) – this almost always means that this encoding should be a compatible superset of ASCII, such as UTF-8 or ISO-8859-1. Note, however, that state-dependent encodings where the same byte values can be used in initial and non-initial shift states may be problematic.

	- Of course, in order to be useful, functions that operate on text may have to make some assumptions about how the string is encoded. Unfortunately, there is much variation on this matter throughout PHP’s functions:

 		- Some functions assume that the string is encoded in some (any) single-byte encoding, but they do not need to interpret those bytes as specific characters. This is case of, for instance, substr(), strpos(), strlen() or strcmp(). Another way to think of these functions is that operate on memory buffers, i.e., they work with bytes and byte offsets.

		- Other functions are passed the encoding of the string, possibly they also assume a default if no such information is given. This is the case of htmlentities() and the majority of the functions in the mbstring extension.

		- Others use the current locale (see setlocale()), but operate byte-by-byte. This is the case of strcasecmp(), strtoupper() and ucfirst(). This means they can be used only with single-byte encodings, as long as the encoding is matched by the locale. For instance strtoupper("á") may return "Á" if the locale is correctly set and á is encoded with a single byte. If it is encoded in UTF-8, the correct result will not be returned and the resulting string may or may not be returned corrupted, depending on the current locale.

		- Finally, they may just assume the string is using a specific encoding, usually UTF-8. This is the case of most functions in the intl extension and in the PCRE extension (in the last case, only when the u modifier is used). Although this is due to their special purpose, the function utf8_decode() assumes a UTF-8 encoding and the function utf8_encode() assumes an ISO-8859-1 encoding.

		- Ultimately, this means writing correct programs using Unicode depends on carefully avoiding functions that will not work and that most likely will corrupt the data and using instead the functions that do behave correctly, generally from the intl and mbstring extensions. However, using functions that can handle Unicode encodings is just the beginning. No matter the functions the language provides, it is essential to know the Unicode specification. For instance, a program that assumes there is only uppercase and lowercase is making a wrong assumption.

-----------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------

Four compound types:	
	- array
		- In PHP an array is an arranged map, a type that connects values to keys. it is used in many ways like for example; it can be considered as an array, list(vestor), hash table(an implementation of a map), dictionary, collection, stack, queue, etc. Trees and multidimensional arrays are possible because array values can be like the other arrays.

	Syntax
		Specifying with array()
Array is created with the help of array() language construct. It takes any number of comma-separated key => value pairs as arguments.

	array(
  	  key  => value,
 	   key2 => value2,
  	  key3 => value3,
	    ...
	)

	- The comma after the last array element is not much needed. This is being done for single-line arrays, i.e. array(1,2) is preferred over array(1,2).  At the same time, the trailing comma is usually being used for multi-line arrays because it lets easier addition of new elements at the end.

A simple array

	<?php
	$array = array(
 	   "foo" => "bar",
	    "bar" => "foo",
	);

	// as of PHP 5.4
	$array = [
	    "foo" => "bar",
 	   "bar" => "foo",
	];
	?>

	The key can either be an integer or a string. The value can be of any type.

	Additionally the following key casts will occur:
		Strings that has a valid decimal integer will be cast to the integer type unless the number is preceded by a + sign.
			Example:
				The key "8" will actually be stored under 8. On the other hand "08" will not be cast, as it isn't a valid decimal integer.
		Floats are also cast to integers meaning that the fractional part will be truncated.
			Example:
				The key 8.7 will actually be stored under 8.
		Bools are cast to integers, too
			Example:
				The key true will actually be stored under 1 and the key false under 0.
		Null will be cast to the empty string
			Example:
				The key null will actually be stored under "".
		Arrays and objects cannot be used as keys. Doing so will result in a warning: Illegal offset type.
The last one will be used if a multiple elements in array declaration uses same key.

Type Casting and Overwriting example
	<?php
	$array = array(
	    1    => "a",
	    "1"  => "b",
	    1.5  => "c",
	    true => "d",
	);
	var_dump($array);
	?>
	The above example will output:

	array(1) {
	  [1]=>
	  string(1) "d"
	}

As all keys are cast to 1, all values will be overwritten to all new elements as the “d” values will only be left over.

PHP cannot differentiate indexed and associative arrays while integer and string keys can be contained by PHP arrays.

Mixed integer and string keys 

	<?php
	$array = array(
	    "foo" => "bar",
	    "bar" => "foo",
 	   100   => -100,
 	   -100  => 100,
	);
	var_dump($array);
	?>

The above example will output:

	array(4) {
	  ["foo"]=>
	  string(3) "bar"
	  ["bar"]=>
	  string(3) "foo"
	  [100]=>
	  int(-100)
	  [-100]=>
	  int(100)
	}

Indexed arrays without key

	<?php
	$array = array("foo", "bar", "hello", "world");
	var_dump($array);
	?>

The above example will output:

	array(4) {
	  [0]=>
	  string(3) "foo"
	  [1]=>
	  string(3) "bar"
	  [2]=>
 	 string(5) "hello"
 	 [3]=>
	  string(5) "world"
	}	

It is possible to specify the key only for some elements and leave it out for others.

Keys not on all elements

	<?php
	$array = array(
 	        "a",
	         "b",
	    6 => "c",
 	        "d",
	);
	var_dump($array);
	?>

The above example will output:

	array(4) {
	  [0]=>
  	string(1) "a"
 	 [1]=>
 	 string(1) "b"
	  [6]=>
 	 string(1) "c"
	  [7]=>
 	 string(1) "d"
	}

The last value “d” was assigned the key 7, this is because the largest integer key before that was 6.

Accessing array elements with square bracket syntax

	- Array elements can be accessed using the array[key] syntax.

Accessing array elements

	<?php
	$array = array(
	    "foo" => "bar",
 	   42    => 24,
 	   "multi" => array(
	         "dimensional" => array(
 	            "array" => "foo"
 	        )
 	   )
	);

	var_dump($array["foo"]);
	var_dump($array[42]);
	var_dump($array["multi"]["dimensional"]["array"]);
	?>

The above example will output:

	string(3) "bar"
	int(24)
	string(3) "foo"

*Note:
Both square brackets and curly braces can be used interchangeably for accessing array elements (e.g. $array[42] and $array{42} will both do the same thing in the example above).

Array Dereferencing 

	<?php
	function getArray() {
	    return array(1, 2, 3);
	}

	// on PHP 5.4
	$secondElement = getArray()[1];

	// previously
	$tmp = getArray();
	$secondElement = $tmp[1];

	// or
	list(, $secondElement) = getArray();
	?>

*Note:
Attempting to access an array key which has not been defined is the same as accessing any other undefined variable: an E_NOTICE-level error message will be issued, and the result will be NULL.

*Note:
Array dereferencing a scalar value which is not a string silently yields NULL, i.e. without issuing an error message.

Creating/modifying with square bracket syntax

	 - An existing array can be known by clearly setting values in it. 

	 - Assigning values to the array is a way of doing it specifying key brackets. Empty pair of brackets ([]) is the outcome of a key being removed.

	$arr[key] = value;
	$arr[] = value;
	// key may be an integer or string
	// value may be any value of any type

	- Other ways in creating an array is when $arr doesn’t exist rather it is being created. However, this method is not much advisable because $arr already has some value for example a string from request variable, thus [] will change its role in becoming now the string access operator because its value stayed in place.

	- In changing a value in particular, use the elements key in assigning a new value. On the other hand, when removing a key/value pair, call the unset() function on it.

	<?php
	$arr = array(5 => 1, 12 => 2);

	$arr[] = 56;    // This is the same as $arr[13] = 56;
               		// at this point of the script

	$arr["x"] = 42; // This adds a new element to
        	        // the array with key "x"
                
	unset($arr[5]); // This removes the element from the array

	unset($arr);    // This deletes the whole array
	?>

*Note:
	As mentioned above, if no key is specified, the maximum of the existing integer indices is taken, and the new key will be that maximum value plus 1 (but at least 0). If no integer indices exist yet, the key will be 0 (zero).

	Note that the maximum integer key used for this need not currently exist in the array. It need only have existed in the array at some time since the last time the array was re-indexed. The following example illustrates:

	<?php
	// Create a simple array.
	$array = array(1, 2, 3, 4, 5);
	print_r($array);

	// Now delete every item, but leave the array itself intact:
	foreach ($array as $i => $value) {
 	   unset($array[$i]);
	}
	print_r($array);

	// Append an item (note that the new key is 5, instead of 0).
	$array[] = 6;
	print_r($array);

	// Re-index:
	$array = array_values($array);
	$array[] = 7;
	print_r($array);
	?>

The above example will output:

	Array
	(
 	   [0] => 1
	   [1] => 2
 	   [2] => 3
 	   [3] => 4
 	   [4] => 5
	)
	Array
	(
	)
	Array
	(
  	  [5] => 6
	)
	Array
	(
	    [0] => 6
	    [1] => 7
	)

Useful functions
	
	- The foreach control structure exists specifically for arrays. It provides an easy way to traverse an array.

*Note:

The unset() function allows removing keys from an array. Be aware that the array will not be reindexed. If a true "remove and shift" behavior is desired, the array can be reindexed using the array_values() function.

	<?php
	$a = array(1 => 'one', 2 => 'two', 3 => 'three');
	unset($a[2]);
	/* will produce an array that would have been defined as
	   $a = array(1 => 'one', 3 => 'three');
	   and NOT
 	  $a = array(1 => 'one', 2 =>'three');
	*/

	$b = array_values($a);
	// Now $b is array(0 => 'one', 1 =>'three')
	?>

Array do's and don'ts

Why is $foo{bar] wrong?

	- $foo[bar] works out but this is wrong for a reason that this code has an undefined constant (bar). PHP automatically changes a bare string(unquoted that do not correspond to any known symbol) with those containing a bare string. Having no particular constant named bar will be replaced in the string bar and will be used in PHP.

*Note: This does not mean to always quote the key. Do not quote keys which are constants or variables, as this will prevent PHP from interpreting them.
	<?php
	error_reporting(E_ALL);
	ini_set('display_errors', true);
	ini_set('html_errors', false);
	// Simple array:
	$array = array(1, 2);
	$count = count($array);
	for ($i = 0; $i < $count; $i++) {
	    echo "\nChecking $i: \n";
	    echo "Bad: " . $array['$i'] . "\n";
	    echo "Good: " . $array[$i] . "\n";
	    echo "Bad: {$array['$i']}\n";
 	   echo "Good: {$array[$i]}\n";
	}
	?>

The above example will output:

	Checking 0: 
	Notice: Undefined index:  $i in /path/to/script.html on line 9
	Bad: 
	Good: 1
	Notice: Undefined index:  $i in /path/to/script.html on line 11
	Bad: 
	Good: 1

	Checking 1: 
	Notice: Undefined index:  $i in /path/to/script.html on line 9
	Bad: 
	Good: 2
	Notice: Undefined index:  $i in /path/to/script.html on line 11
	Bad: 
	Good: 2
	More examples to demonstrate this behaviour:
	<?php
	// Show all errors
	error_reporting(E_ALL);

	$arr = array('fruit' => 'apple', 'veggie' => 'carrot');

	// Correct
	print $arr['fruit'];  // apple
	print $arr['veggie']; // carrot

	// Incorrect.  This works but also throws a PHP error of level E_NOTICE because
	// of an undefined constant named fruit
	// 
	// Notice: Use of undefined constant fruit - assumed 'fruit' in...
	print $arr[fruit];    // apple

	// This defines a constant to demonstrate what's going on.  The value 'veggie'
	// is assigned to a constant named fruit.
define('fruit', 'veggie');

	// Notice the difference now
	print $arr['fruit'];  // apple
	print $arr[fruit];    // carrot

	// The following is okay, as it's inside a string. Constants are not looked for
	// within strings, so no E_NOTICE occurs here
	print "Hello $arr[fruit]";      // Hello apple

	// With one exception: braces surrounding arrays within strings allows constants
	// to be interpreted
	print "Hello {$arr[fruit]}";    // Hello carrot
	print "Hello {$arr['fruit']}";  // Hello apple

	// This will not work, and will result in a parse error, such as:
	// Parse error: parse error, expecting T_STRING' or T_VARIABLE' or T_NUM_STRING'
	// This of course applies to using superglobals in strings as well
	print "Hello $arr['fruit']";
	print "Hello $_GET['foo']";

	// Concatenation is another option
	print "Hello " . $arr['fruit']; // Hello apple
	?>

	- Uses will be shown instantly when error_reporting is set to E_NOTICE level errors when setting it to E_ALL for example.

	- That is why what is inside the brackets (‘[‘ and ‘]’) must be an expression as being stated in the syntax section.

	<?php
	echo $arr[somefunc($bar)];
	?>

	- This is an example of using a function return value as the array index. PHP also knows about constants:

	<?php
	$error_descriptions[E_ERROR]   = "A fatal error has occurred";
	$error_descriptions[E_WARNING] = "PHP issued a warning";
	$error_descriptions[E_NOTICE]  = "This is just an informal notice";
	?>


	- Note that E_ERROR is also a valid identifier, just like bar because E_ERROR equals 1, etc.(as shown in the first example).

	<?php
	$error_descriptions[1] = "A fatal error has occurred";
	$error_descriptions[2] = "PHP issued a warning";
	$error_descriptions[8] = "This is just an informal notice";
	?>

So why is it bad then?

	- PHP team might want to add another constant or keyword, or constant in other code may interfere at some point in the future. As an example, words like empty and default is somewhat wrong for use because they are reserved keywords.

Converting to array

	- Transforming a value to an array results in an array with a single element with index zero and the value of the scalar which was converted, with that (array)$scalarValue is exactly the same as array($scalarValue).

	- If an object is converted to an array, the result is an array whose elements are the object's properties. The keys are the member variable names, with a few notable exceptions: integer properties are unaccessible; private variables have the class name prepended to the variable name; protected variables have a '*' prepended to the variable name. These prepended values have null bytes on either side. This can result in some unexpected behaviour.

	<?php

	class A {
	    private $A; // This will become '\0A\0A'
	}

	class B extends A {
	    private $A; // This will become '\0B\0A'
 	   public $AA; // This will become 'AA'
	}

	var_dump((array) new B());
	?>

Even though one of them is actually named ‘\0A\0A’ it appears as if they have two keys named ‘AA’.

Comparing 

	- It is possible to compare arrays with the array_diff() function and with array operators.

Examples
The array type in PHP is very versatile.

	<?php
	// This:
	$a = array( 'color' => 'red',
  	          'taste' => 'sweet',
 	           'shape' => 'round',
  	          'name'  => 'apple',
   	         4        // key will be 0
    	      );

	$b = array('a', 'b', 'c');

	// . . .is completely equivalent with this:
	$a = array();
	$a['color'] = 'red';
	$a['taste'] = 'sweet';
	$a['shape'] = 'round';
	$a['name']  = 'apple';
	$a[]        = 4;        // key will be 0

	$b = array();
	$b[] = 'a';
	$b[] = 'b';
	$b[] = 'c';

	// After the above code is executed, $a will be the array
	// array('color' => 'red', 'taste' => 'sweet', 'shape' => 'round', 
	// 'name' => 'apple', 0 => 4), and $b will be the array 
	// array(0 => 'a', 1 => 'b', 2 => 'c'), or simply array('a', 'b', 'c').
	?>

Using array()

	<?php
	// Array as (property-)map
	$map = array( 'version'    => 4,
	              'OS'         => 'Linux',
 	             'lang'       => 'english',
  	            'short_tags' => true
 	           );
 	           
	// strictly numerical keys
	$array = array( 7,
 	               8,
   	             0,
  	              156,
   	             -10
   	           );
	// this is the same as array(0 => 7, 1 => 8, ...)

	$switching = array(         10, // key = 0
                    5    =>  6,
                    3    =>  7, 
                    'a'  =>  4,
                            11, // key = 6 (maximum of integer-indices was 5)
                    '8'  =>  2, // key = 8 (integer!)
                    '02' => 77, // key = '02'
                    0    => 12  // the value 10 will be overwritten by 12
                  );
                  
	// empty array
	$empty = array();         
	?>

Collection 

	<?php
	$colors = array('red', 'blue', 'green', 'yellow');

	foreach ($colors as $color) {
	    echo "Do you like $color?\n";
	}

	?>

The above example will output:

	Do you like red?
	Do you like blue?
	Do you like green?
	Do you like yellow?

It is possible to change the values of the array by passing them by reference.

Changing element in the loop 
	
	<?php
	foreach ($colors as &$color) {
 	   $color = strtoupper($color);
	}
	unset($color); /* ensure that following writes to
	$color will not modify the last array element */

	print_r($colors);
	?>

The above example will output:

	Array
	(
  	  [0] => RED
 	   [1] => BLUE
 	   [2] => GREEN
 	   [3] => YELLOW
	)

This example creates a one-based array.

One-based index

	<?php
	$firstquarter  = array(1 => 'January', 'February', 'March');
	print_r($firstquarter);
	?>

The above example will output:

	Array 
	(
	    [1] => 'January'
	    [2] => 'February'
	    [3] => 'March'
	)

Filling an array

	<?php
	// fill an array with all items from a directory
	$handle = opendir('.');
	while (false !== ($file = readdir($handle))) {
  	  $files[] = $file;
	}
	closedir($handle); 
	?>
	
	Arrays are ordered but can be changed by using various sorting functions. In counting the number of items in an array, count() function can be utilized.

Sorting an array

	<?php
	sort($files);
	print_r($files);
	?>

	Since the value of an array can portray anything, it can become another array also. This makes the creation of recursive and multi-dimensional arrays possible.

Recursive and multi-dimensional arrays

	<?php
	$fruits = array ( "fruits"  => array ( "a" => "orange",
                                       "b" => "banana",
                                       "c" => "apple"
                                     ),
                  "numbers" => array ( 1,
                                       2,
                                       3,
                                       4,
                                       5,
                                       6
                                     ),
                  "holes"   => array (      "first",
                                       5 => "second",
                                            "third"
                                     )
                );

	// Some examples to address values in the array above 
		echo $fruits["holes"][5];    // prints "second"
		echo $fruits["fruits"]["a"]; // prints "orange"
	unset($fruits["holes"][0]);  // remove "first"

	// Create a new multi-dimensional array
	$juices["apple"]["green"] = "good"; 
	?>

Array assignment always involves value copying. Use the reference operator to copy an array by reference.

	<?php
	$arr1 = array(2, 3);
	$arr2 = $arr1;
	$arr2[] = 4; // $arr2 is changed,
 	            // $arr1 is still array(2, 3)
             
	$arr3 = &$arr1;
	$arr3[] = 4; // now $arr1 and $arr3 are the same
	?>

--------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------

	- object
		- To create a new object, use the new statement to instantiate a class:
	<?php
	class foo
	{
   	 function do_foo()
    	{
        echo "Doing foo."; 
    	}
	}

	$bar = new foo;
	$bar->do_foo();
	?>
Converting to object
	- Object to Object – Not modified
	- Value of any other type to Object – instance of the stdClass built-in class created
	- NULL – instance is Empty
	- Array that is being transformed to an object having properties named by keys and corresponding values, with the exception of numeric keys which will be inaccessible unless iterated.

	<?php
	$obj = (object) array('1' => 'foo');
	var_dump(isset($obj->{'1'})); // outputs 'bool(false)'
	var_dump(key($obj)); // outputs 'int(1)'
	?>

For any other value, a member variable named scalar will contain the value.

	<?php
	$obj = (object) 'ciao';
	echo $obj->scalar;  // outputs 'ciao'
	?>	

--------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------
	- callable
		- - Call_user_func() or usort() are just few functions that takes user-defined callback functions as parameter. Callback functions, object methods and statistic class methods can not only be simple functions.

        	- A PHP function is passed by its name as a string, any built-in or user-defined function can be utilized but not of language constructs such as:

	- array()
 	- echo
	- empty()
	- eval()
	- exit()
	- isset()
	- list()
	- print
	- unset()

	- A method of an instantiated object is transferred as an array having an object at index 0 and the method name at index 1. Protected and private methods are allowed to access from within a class.

	- Static class methods can also be transferred with no instantiating object of that class by passing a class name instead of an object at index 0. As of PHP 5.2.3, it is possible to pass ‘ClassName::methodName’.

 	- Aside from the usual user-defined function, anonymous functions can be passed to a callback parameter.

Callback function examples

	<?php

	// An example callback function
	function my_callback_function() {
	    echo 'hello world!';
	}

	// An example callback method
	class MyClass {
	    static function myCallbackMethod() {
	        echo 'Hello World!';
	    }
	}

	// Type 1: Simple callback
	call_user_func('my_callback_function');

	// Type 2: Static class method call
	call_user_func(array('MyClass', 'myCallbackMethod'));

	// Type 3: Object method call
	$obj = new MyClass();
	call_user_func(array($obj, 'myCallbackMethod'));

	// Type 4: Static class method call (As of PHP 5.2.3)
	call_user_func('MyClass::myCallbackMethod');

	// Type 5: Relative static class method call (As of PHP 5.3.0)
	class A {
 	   public static function who() {
 	       echo "A\n";
 	   }
	}

	class B extends A {
 	   public static function who() {
	        echo "B\n";
	    }
	}

	call_user_func(array('B', 'parent::who')); // A

	// Type 6: Objects implementing __invoke can be used as callables (since PHP 5.3)
	class C {
   	 public function __invoke($name) {
  	      echo 'Hello ', $name, "\n";
  	  }
	}	

	$c = new C();
	call_user_func($c, 'PHP!');
	?>

Callback example using a Closure

	<?php
	// Our closure
	$double = function($a) {
	    return $a * 2;
	};

	// This is our range of numbers
	$numbers = range(1, 5);

	// Use the closure as a callback here to
	// double the size of each element in our
	// range
	$new_numbers = array_map($double, $numbers);

	print implode(' ', $new_numbers);
	?>
	The above example will output:
	2 4 6 8 10

--------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------
	- iterable
		- A pseudo- type established in PHP 7.1 that takes any array or object implementing the Traversable interface in which this two are iterable using foreach and can be utilized with yield from within a generator.

	Using Iterables 
		-Iterables as a parameter can be a great help specially in knowing that a particular function needs a set of values but a part of it does not give much attention about the form of the value set because it will be utilized with foreach. A TypeError will be thrown if a value is not an array or instance.

Iterable parameter type example
	<?php

	function foo(iterable $iterable) {
    		foreach ($iterable as $value) {
        	// ...
    		} 
	}

	?>

Iterable parameter default value example
	<?php

	function foo(iterable $iterable = []) {
    		// ...
	}

	?>

Iterable can also be used as a return type to indicate a function will return an iterable value. If the returned value is not an array or instance of Traversable, a TypeError will be thrown.

Iterable return type example 
	<?php

	function bar(): iterable {
    		return [1, 2, 3];
	}

	?>

Functions declaring iterable as a return type may also be generators.

Iterable generator return type example
	<?php

	function gen(): iterable {
    		yield 1;
    		yield 2;
	    	yield 3;
	}

	?>

Iterable Type Variance

	- Classes extending or implementing may broaden methods using array or Traversable as parameter types to iterable or narrow return types from iterable to array or Traversable.

Iterable type variance example

	<?php

	interface Example {
    		public function method(array $array): iterable;
	}

	class ExampleImplementation implements Example {
    		public function method(iterable $iterable): array {
        		// Parameter broadened and return type narrowed.
    		}
	}

	?>

=================================================================================================================================================
And Finally two special types:

	- resource 
		-Considered as a special variable holding a reference to an external resource, that are created and used by special functions.

Converting to resource
	- As resource variables hold special handles to opened files, database connections, image canvas areas and the like, converting to a resource makes no sense.

Freeing Resources
	- A resource with no more references to it is detected automatically, and it is freed by the garbage collector. For this reason, it is rarely necessary to free the memory manually with the help of reference- counting system.
-------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------
	- NULL
		- It represents a variable having no value and the only possible value of type null.

	Variable that is null to be considered are as follows:
		- it has been assigned the constant NULL.
		- it has not been set to any value yet.
		- it has been unset().

Syntax
	- There is only one value of type null, and that is the case-insensitive constant NULL.
	
	<?php
	$var = NULL;       
	?>

Casting to Null
	- Casting a variable to null using (unset) $var will not remove the variable or unset its value. It will only return a NULL value.

==================================================================================================================================================
This manual also introduces some pseudo-types for readability reasons:

PSEUDO TYPE
	- They are keywords that are being used in the PHP documentation in knowing the types or values an argument can have but they are not primitives of the PHP language. Thus, pseudo types as typehints cannot be utilize in your own custom functions.

	- mixed
		- It tells that a parameter may take multiple types but not all of it.

Example:
gettype() – accepts all PHP types
str_replace – accepts string and arrays
--------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------
	- number
		- It tells that a parameter can be either integer or float.
--------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------

	- callback (aka callable)
		-Before callable type was introduced by PHP 5.4, callback pseudo type was first used in the documentation, having it exactly the same.
--------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------
	- array| object
		- array|object indicates that a parameter can be either array or object.
--------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------
	- void
		-Return type – the return value is useless
Parameter list – the function doesn’t accept any parameters

…
$... in function prototypes means and so on, this variable name is used when a function can take an endless number of arguments.

--------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------

And the pseudo-variable $ ....

	- Some References to the type " double " may remain in the manual. Consider double the same as float.

*Note: To check the type and value of an expression, use the var_dump() function.

To get a human-readable representation of a type for debugging, use the gettype() function. To check for a certain type, do not use gettype(), but rather the is_type functions. Some examples:

	<?php
	$a_bool = TRUE;   // a boolean
	$a_str  = "foo";  // a string
	$a_str2 = 'foo';  // a string
	$an_int = 12;     // an integer

	echo gettype($a_bool); // prints out:  boolean
	echo gettype($a_str);  // prints out:  string

	// If this is an integer, increment it by four
	if (is_int($an_int)) {
 	   $an_int += 4;
	}

	// If $a_bool is a string, print it out
	// (does not print out anything)
	if (is_string($a_bool)) {
	    echo "String: $a_bool";
	}
	?>

Note that a variable may be evaluated with different values in certain situations, depending on what type it is at the time. For more information, see the section on Type Juggling. The type comparison tables may also be useful, as they show examples of various type-related comparisons.
=========================================================================

TYPE JUGGLING

	- A clear sort definition is not much needed in variable declaration of PHP, variable’s type is known by the context in which it is used. It explains that if a string is assigned to variable $var, $var still turns out to be a string and if an integer value is then assigned to $var, it also still becomes an integer.

	- Multiplication operator ‘x’ is an example for PHP automatic type conversion. If either operand is a float, then both operands are evaluated as floats and the outcome will also be a float if not, the operands will be interpreted as integers and the result will also be an integer. Remember that there will be no change in the types of operands themselves, only on how the operands are assessed and the type of expression itself that has a change.
	
	<?php
	$foo = "1";  // $foo is string (ASCII 49)
	$foo *= 2;   // $foo is now an integer (2)
	$foo = $foo * 1.3;  // $foo is now a float (2.6)
	$foo = 5 * "10 Little Piggies"; // $foo is integer (50)
	$foo = 5 * "10 Small Pigs";     // $foo is integer (50)
	?>

If the last two examples above seem odd, see String conversion to numbers.

To make an evaluation of a variable with a certain type, see the section on Type casting. Likewise, to change the type of a variable, see settype() function.

In making a try for an example in this section, use var_dump() function.

*Note:
The behaviour of an automatic conversion to array is currently undefined.
Also, because PHP supports indexing into strings via offsets using the same syntax as array indexing, the following example holds true for all PHP versions:

	<?php
	$a    = 'car'; // $a is a string
	$a[0] = 'b';   // $a is still a string
	echo $a;       // bar
	?>

See the section titled String access by character for more information.

Type Casting

	- Type casting works well on PHP like in C: the name of the desired type being chosen is written in parentheses before the variable that will be cast.

	<?php
	$foo = 10;   // $foo is an integer
	$bar = (boolean) $foo;   // $bar is a boolean
	?>

The casts allowed are:

(int), (integer) - cast to integer
(bool), (boolean) - cast to boolean
(float), (double), (real) - cast to float
(string) - cast to string
(array) - cast to array
(object) - cast to object
(unset) - cast to NULL

(binary) casting and b prefix forward support was added in PHP 5.2.1. Remember that (binary) and (string) are both important but must not always depend on.

The (unset) cast has been deprecated as of PHP 7.2.0. The (unset) cast is the same as NULL in assigning a value to the variable or call. However, (unset) cast is removed as it reaches PHP 8.0.0.

Note that tabs and spaces are allowed inside the parentheses, so the following are functionally equivalent:
	
	<?php
	$foo = (int) $bar;
	$foo = ( int ) $bar;
	?>

Casting literal strings and variables to binary strings:
	
	<?php
	$binary = (binary) $string;
	$binary = b"binary string";
	?>